Inventory of the Wang Sheng papers
Hoover Institution Archives
Wang Sheng papers
1950-2000
2013C5
Hoover Institution Archives
10 manuscript boxes, 4 oversize boxes (6.6 linear feet)
Diaries, photographs, and writings relating to Taiwanese military policy and to confidential relations between Taiwan and the People's Republic of China.
Wang, Sheng, 1917-
Access
The collection is open for research.
The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos or films during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all audiovisual material is immediately accessible.
Acquisition Information
Acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives in 2012.
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog at http://searchworks.stanford.edu/. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in the online catalog is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Biographical Note
Wang Sheng (1917-2006) was a lieutenant general in the People's Republic of China army and director of the General Political Warfare Department from 1975 to 1983.
Wang was born in Longnan County, Jiangxi Province. In 1939 he joined the Kuomintang (KMT) and was sent to join the Three Principles of the People Youth Corps Training Course, run by Chiang Ching-kuo. After finishing the course, Wang was chosen to work for Chiang, which he did for the next fifty years, including taking care of Chiang's twin sons.
In the early 1950s, Wang established the precursor to the General Political Warfare College, the elite training school for the KMT army and party cadres. Being second in command of the civil-military programs, welfare, and services section of Chiang Ching-kuo's cadre system, Wang's main task was laying the foundation for the China Youth Corps under Chiang's leadership. Wang thus spent most of the later 1950s and 1960s training army political cadres in the General Political Warfare College, which allowed him to develop a mentoring relationship with rising officers throughout the armed forces. In 1953, Wang was named assistant commandant (i.e., provost) and in January 1954 was made a major general. In 1960, Wang became deputy director of the General Political Warfare Department at the Ministry of National Defense; in mid-1961 he was promoted to lieutenant general and became the executive deputy director. He was promoted to director in April 1975, the same month in which Chiang Kai-shek died. Wang served as director of the General Political Warfare Department of the Republic of China's Armed Forces until 1983, during which time he became one of Chiang Ching-kuo's most trusted advisers, frequently undertaking secret military and intelligence assignments on behalf of the Taiwanese government.
In 1979, Wang was assigned to lead a special unit within the KMT, the Liu Shaokang Office, aimed at dealing with Chinese Communist peace overtures to Taiwan and Beijing's newly proposed united front. This office was so powerful that it was described in Taiwan's political arena as the inner court of the KMT party headquarters, and Wang's position was second only to that of President Chiang Ching-kuo. In the early 1980s, as Chiang's health failed, Wang was invited by the US government to visit the United States and meet high officials from the Reagan administration. As Wang toured the United States, however, certain military-intelligence quarters in Washington, DC and mass media such as Newsweek began describing him as Chiang's heir apparent. In August 1983, Chiang sent Wang to Paraguay as Taiwan's ambassador; Wang did not return to Taiwan until Chiang's death in January 1988. Wang died in Taipei in 2006.
Scope and Content of Collection
This collection contains fifty-one volumes of Wang Sheng's personal diaries, dating from the early 1950s to 2000, and twenty-four volumes of official files, speeches, minutes, correspondence, and photographs. They document Wang's unique position in Taiwan's political and military-intelligence arenas and reveal the secret role Taiwan and the KMT played in the Cold War's East Asian theater.
Taiwan--Military policy.; Taiwan--Politics and government.; Taiwan--Foreign relations--China.; China--Foreign relations--Taiwan.
- Diaries, 1950-2000
  - 1950 October-December 自由日記 (Box 1)
  - 1951 中華民囯四十年國民日記 (Box 1)
  - 1954 (two volumes) 日記 (Box 1)
  - 1955 中華民囯四十四年日記 (Box 1)
  - 1956 中華民囯四十五年日記 (Box 1)
  - 1957 中華民囯四十六年日記 (Box 1)
  - 1959 中華民囯四十八年日記 (Box 1)
  - 1960 中華民囯四十九年日記 (Box 1)
  - 1961 青年日記 (Box 1)
  - 1962 青年日記 (Box 1)
  - 1963 中華民囯五十二年日記 (Box 1)
  - 1964 中華民囯五十三年日記 (Box 2)
  - 1965 中華民囯五十四年日記 (Box 2)
  - 1966 中華民囯五十五年日記 (Box 2)
  - 1967 中華民囯五十六年日記 (Box 2)
  - 1968 中華民囯五十七年日記 (Box 2)
  - 1969 中華民囯五十八年日記 (Box 2)
  - 1970 中華民囯五十九年日記 (Box 2)
  - 1971 中華民囯六十年日記 (Box 2)
  - 1972 中華民囯六十一年日記 (Box 2)
  - 1973 中華民囯六十二年日記 (Box 2)
  - 1974 中華民囯六十三年日記 (Box 2)
  - 1975 中華民囯六十四年日記 (Box 2)
  - 1976 中華民囯六十五年日記 (Box 2)
  - 1977 中華民囯六十六年日記 (Box 2)
  - 1978 中華民囯六十七年日記 (Box 2)
  - 1979 中華民囯六十八年日記 (Box 2)
  - 1980 年鑒日記 (Box 3)
  - 1981 年鑒日記 (Box 3)
  - 1982 年鑒日記 (Box 3)
  - 1983 年鑒日記 (Box 3)
  - 1984 年鑒日記 (Box 3)
  - 1985 年鑒日記 (Box 3)
  - 1986 年鑒日記 (Box 3)
  - 1987 年鑒日記 (Box 3)
  - 1988 年鑒日記 (Box 3)
  - 1989 年鑒日記 (Box 3)
  - 1990 年鑒日記 (Box 3)
  - 1991 年鑒日記 (Box 3)
  - 1993 年鑒日記 (Box 3)
  - 1994 年鑒日記 (Box 3)
  - 1995 年鑒日記 (Box 4)
  - 1996 年鑒日記 (Box 4)
  - 1997 年鑒日記 (Box 4)
  - 1998 年鑒日記 (Box 4)
  - 1999 年鑒日記 (Box 4)
  - 2000 年鑒日記 (Box 4)
- Regulation on Disguised CCP at International Airports, Key Points in Fighting Overseas Enemies, Key Points on Psychological Warfare Against CCP at Present Stage 國際機場處理匪偽人員過境規定，海外對敵鬥爭工作要點，現階段對匪心戰指導要點, 1980 (Box-folder 5: 1)
- Outline on Enhancing Struggle Against Enemies at the Present Stage, Solution to CCP's Conspiracy of "3 Circulation" and "Four Communications" 現階段加強對敵鬥爭工作綱要，共匪“三通”“四流”統戰陰謀之對策, 1980 (Box-folder 5: 2)
- Outline on Enhancing Struggle Against Enemies at the Present Stage, Outline on Persuading CCP to Abandon Communist Movements, Outline on Enlarging and Unifying Overseas Chinese Scholars and Immigrants 現階段加強對敵鬥爭工作綱要，苦勸中共放棄共產主義運動推行計劃綱要，擴大爭取團結海外學人、僑領計劃綱要, 1980 (Box-folder 5: 3)
- Implementation Summary on Action against Beijing CCP's Trial of Lin Biao and Gang of Four, Key Points in Fighting Oversea Enemies 針對北平匪審匪醜劇展開攻擊行動實施綱要，加強海外對敵鬥爭工作要點, 1980 (Box-folder 5: 4)
- Outline on Enhancing Struggle Against Enemies, Liu Shaokang Office Self-Criticism 加強對敵鬥爭工作綱要，劉少康辦公室檢討, 1982-1983 (Box-folder 5: 5)
- Observation on National People's Congress Standing Committee's Draft Amendment to Constitution with Study on Solutions, Self-Criticism on Oversea Communication by Chinese in Taiwan and Suggestions on Preventing People from Smuggling into Mainland 對偽人大常委會通過偽憲法修改草案之初步觀察及應採取措施之研究，在台定居國人經由海外通信及潛往匪區狀況檢討及防制建議, 1982 (Box-folder 5: 6)
- Liu Shaokang Office documents 劉少康辦公室文件, 1982 (Box-folder 5: 7)
- Current Nation Dividing Movements and Study on Solutions, Emergency Processing Procedures 當前國内分歧活動概況與對策研究，突發事件立即處理程序, 1981-1982 (Box-folder 5: 8)
- CCP's New Solution on Attacking Our United Front, Key Points on Enhancing Works 共匪對我新統戰攻勢對策，強化工作實施要點, 1981 (Box-folder 5: 9)
- Political Battle Innovation Solutions of the National Army, Zhuang Jing Self-Strengthening Movement Solutions, the Changing World and Our Due Efforts manuscripts 國軍政治作戰革新方案 莊敬自強運動方案 當前世局演變和我們應有的努力 手稿 (Box 6)
- General Wang visiting Korea 主任王上將訪問大韓民囯專輯, 1981 (Box 6)
- Accepting honorary degree of law from Dankook University in Korea 中華民囯六十一年十一月三日接受大韓民囯檀囯大學 贈予榮譽法學博士專輯, 1972 November 3 (Box 7)
- General Wang visiting Korea and Japan 主任王上將訪問韓國及日本專輯, 1977 (Box 7)
- Visiting Cambodia 訪問高棉資料, 1972 (Box 8)
- General Wang visiting Indonesia 主任王上將訪問印度尼西亞專輯, 1975 (Box 8)
- Nation Army Politics and Warfare Conference manuscripts 國軍六十六年政戰會議資料手稿, 1977 (Box 9)
- Chinese KMT Special Party Branch 5th Congress materials 中國國民黨特種黨部第五次代表大會資料, 1969 (Box 9)
- Manuscripts of Wang Shikai on the 7th Congress Meeting 王師凱第七次代表大會資料手稿, 1975 (Box 10)
- Collection of General Wang's visit to Thailand and Malaysia 主任王上將訪問泰國及馬來西亞專輯, 1973 (Box 10)
- Correspondence with Vietnam 越南函件, 1962-1968 (Box 10)
- How to Defeat Enemies with Thoughts 如何在思想戰綫上戰勝敵人, 1972 (Box 11)
- General Wang's visit to South Africa 主任王上將訪問南非共和國, 1970 (Box 11)
- Military Meeting manuscripts of the National Army 囯軍六十四年軍事會議資料手稿, 1975 (Box 12)
- Reports on visiting the United States (2) 訪美報告（二）, 1969 (Box 12)
- Manuscripts of the 6th Cultural Conference of the National Army 國軍第六屆文藝大會資料手稿, 1973 (Box 12)
- Executive General Wang visiting Khmer (Cambodia) and Thailand 執行官王上將訪問高棉及泰國專輯, 1974 (Box 13)
- Politics and war meeting manuscripts of the National Army 囯軍六十五年政戰會議資料手稿, 1976 (Box 13)
- General Wang visiting the Phillipines 主任王上將訪問菲律賓專輯, 1979 (Box 13)
- Special Party Branch 6th Congress Meeting manuscripts 特種黨部第六次代表大會資料手稿, 1972 (Box 14)
- Reports on visiting the United States (1) 訪美報告（一）,（三）, 1969 (Box 14)